Pamela Digby Churchill Hayward Harriman Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
The Subject File series contains files relating to Democratic committees and organizations, Democratic National Conventions, party conferences and meetings, political analysts and newsletters, political campaigns of various candidates, and a variety of topics including campaign finance, political action committees, polling, and women in politics. The series also features a large reference file of election-year data from 1980 to 1990. Correspondence, memoranda, minutes, and reports from the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee, Democratic Governors' Association, Democratic National Committee, and Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee provide insight into the evolution of Democratic strategy in the 1980s and the ways in which the Democrats for the 80's supported these efforts. Among the project initiatives funded by the Democrats for the 80's was the establishment of the Harriman Communications Center which sought to make state-of-the-art communication technology available to Democratic candidates and members of Congress. Files on the Democratic National Conventions include related material on efforts to improve communications at the 1988 and 1992 conventions. Other topics covered in the Subject File include her membership on the Commission on Presidential Debates from 1987 to 1993 and her support as national co-chair of Bill Clinton's presidential campaign in 1992. The series contains memoranda, correspondence, and talking points from the campaign, and post-election letters from individuals seeking appointments in the new administration.
The operations of the Democrats for the 80's and the shaping of its priorities are documented in the Administrative File series. A large chronological arranged by year contains correspondence, memoranda, board minutes, reports, financial records, and lists of political contributions to candidates by the political action committee and Harriman personally. The founding of the Democrats for the 80's is detailed in chronological files for 1980 while its dissolution is covered in those for 1990. Other material in the series includes bylaws, board lists and resolutions, brochures and newsletters, contributor lists, Federal Election Commission and non-federal filings, office memoranda, and procedural manuals. Legal guidance on federal and state laws governing political action committees is found in a file of correspondence with attorneys for the Democrats for the 80's. Talking points in a press file trace how the political action committee defined itself, its activities, and its political message. The series also contains transcripts of some of the committee's early events and meetings. Washington insider Janet A. Howard served as the political action committee's third executive director. A large chronological file under her name was assembled from unfiled correspondence, reports, notes, and printed matter and reflects her busy schedule and the full array of her activities.
The Project File series features some of the Democrats for the 80's major initiatives. The committee raised funds for federal campaigns as well as those for local and statewide office. Beginning in 1982, it concentrated its fund-raising efforts on Senate candidates, launching the Win the Senate '84 campaign and, in 1984, the Senate Majority '86 initiative. Both projects were supported by direct-mail campaigns well documented in the series. One of the earliest priorities of the Democrats for the 80's was an effort to counter the influence of New Right conservatism in the Republican Party. The Project File includes research files and drafts of a 1981 New Right Manual that provided Democratic candidates with information and talking points on conservative political groups. Related correspondence with and about the National Conservative Political Action Committee, a primary focus of this campaign, is available in the Subject File. In 1982, the Democrats for the 80's produced a more general Democratic Fact Book for use by candidates. Included are working files from the 1982 edition, as well as from its 1984 and 1986 revisions. The Democrats for the 80's partnered with the Democratic National Committee and Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee in 1983 in analyzing the legislative records of Republican incumbents in key Senate races. Copies of the reports on Colorado, Illinois, Maine, Mississippi, and New Hampshire are available in the series. The Democrats for the 80's also launched various media campaigns, producing radio and television advertisements and short films, the earliest of which were aimed at the New Right conservatism. A fund-raising campaign to pay for satellite technology at the Harriman Communications Center followed in 1987. The renamed Democrats for the 90's undertook a series of national polling projects in 1989-1990 that included full-scale national polls on voter attitudes, perceptions of the Democratic Party, and the testing of themes. Smaller surveys and focus groups gauged voter opinions on campaign finance reform, capital gains tax cuts, medicare catastrophic coverage, and other issues. The polling projects were coordinated by Peter D. Hart. Finally, files from two major fund-raising events, the celebration of W. Averell Harriman's ninetieth birthday in 1981 and a Democratic gala at the Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts in 1990, are included in the series because of the size of the events and the complexity of their planning.
The Event File series contains working files from other events, most of which were hosted by the Harrimans and the Democrats for the 80's. The series complements material found in the Scheduling and Travel File in Part I, providing a fuller record through correspondence, memoranda, lists of attendees, financial records, invitations, programs, notes, photographs, seating charts, speeches, publicity, and news clippings. The types of events documented in the series include fund-raising dinners, lunches, breakfasts, receptions, garden parties, and "issue evenings," small gatherings in the Harriman home that featured talks by prominent Democratic leaders. Other event files include material from Democratic National Conventions and election-night gatherings hosted by the Harrimans in their home. Pamela Harriman held a major fund-raising event for Bill Clinton and Al Gore at her estate in Middleburg, Virginia, in September 1992 and a dinner for the president-elect during the Clintons' first trip to Washington after the election. Both events are documented in the series.
The Lists series contains lists from a wide variety of sources including political candidates, office holders, Democratic Party committees and organizations, political action committees, lobbyists, labor unions, corporations, industries, foundations, institutions, and religious organizations. The original titles of the lists or those supplied by the Democrats for the 80's have been retained. Although the use of these lists by the Democrats for the 80's is rarely indicated, they were most likely culled for fund-raising campaigns, invitation lists, and general networking. Database lists created by the Democrats for the 80's are also included as well as lists identified as "Harriman contacts" that are filed by state.
The collection contains a small Digital Files series. The digital content was originally stored on thirty-nine 5.25" disks and comprises just over one thousand files dating from 1982 to 1990. Several disks represent an attempt to systematically backup files from a staff member's personal computer. The remainder are more random assortments of the office's work product. Word-processed documents include drafts of fund-raising letters and event correspondence, biographical statements, newsletters, press releases, speeches, and talking points. Topics include the Party of the Decade at the Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts, annual dinners, and other events hosted by the Democrats for the 80's, the National Polling Project, and satellite communication projects. Also included are lists of names and addresses and databases of contributors dated 1985-1986. Data from three magnetic tape reels are currently unprocessed and unavailable.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in sixteen series:
Part I:
Personal and Family Papers, 1920-1997
General Correspondence,1951-1995
Ambassadorial File, 1992-1997
Speeches and Writings, 1973-1992
Scheduling and Travel, 1959-1997
Miscellany, 1909-1997
Artifact, 1967
Classified,1944-1996
Oversize, 1947-1997
Part II:
Subject File, 1968-1993
Administrative File, 1973-1993
Project File, 1976-1992
Event File, 1978-1992
Lists, 1974-1993
Digital Files, 1982-1990
Oversize, 1976-1988
Container List
- Part I: Personal and Family Papers, 1920-1997 (Box I:1-I:34)
  - Family Papers, 1932-1997 (Box I:1-I:25)
    Correspondence, notes, lists, speeches and writings, photographs, and printed matter pertaining to the Churchill, Digby, Hayward, Harriman, and Whitney families.
    Arranged alphabetically by name of family and alphabetically thereunder by name of individual.
    - Churchill family
      - Churchill, Arabella, 1971-1972, 1987-1991
      - Churchill, Jennie Spencer (granddaughter), 1970-1996, undated, (4 folders)
      - Churchill, John Gerard Averell ("Jack") (grandson), 1975-1997, undated, (2 folders)
      - Churchill, Marina (granddaughter), 1970-1996, undated, (3 folders) (Box I:2)
      - Churchill, Minnie d'Erlanger (daughter-in-law)
        - 1964-1993 See Containers I:2-I:4, Churchill, Winston S. and Minnie d'Erlanger
        - 1994-1996
      - Churchill, Peregrine S., 1991, undated
      - Churchill, Randolph Leonard (grandson), 1971-1996, undated, (5 folders)
      - Churchill, Randolph S. (husband), 1943-1945, 1964-1966
      - Churchill, Sarah, 1975, 1982-1983
      - Churchill, Winston (father-in-law) and Clementine (mother-in-law), 1940-1979, undated, (2 folders)
      - Churchill, Winston S. (son) and Minnie d'Erlanger (daughter-in-law)
        - Correspondence
          - circa 1945-1946, 1951, 1959, (2 folders)
          - 1960-1971 See also Part I: Oversize, (16 folders) (Box I:3)
          - 1972-1976, (11 folders) (Box I:4)
          - 1977
            - Jan.-June, (2 folders)
            - July-Dec., (2 folders) (Box I:5)
          - 1978-1987, (15 folders)
          - 1988-1997, (16 folders) (Box I:6)
        - Miscellany See Classified (Box I:7)
        - Printed matter
          - News clippings
            - 1963-1971, (3 folders)
            - 1972-1983 (Box I:8)
          - Political ephemera, 1980s-1990s
      - D'Erlanger, Gladys ("Smut"), 1971-1981, undated
      - Martin, Marion, 1961-1982, undated, (3 folders)
      - Sandys, Edwina, 1976-1993, undated
      - Soames, Mary, 1944, 1975-1993, undated
      - Spencer-Churchill, John, 11th Duke of Marlborough, 1962-1963, 1973-1977, 1985-1990
    - Digby family (Box I:9)
      - Digby, Edward (brother) and Dione, 1961-1996, undated, (5 folders)
      - Digby, Edward Kenelm (father) and Constance Pamela Alice Bruce (mother), 1945, 1954-1967, 1976-1978, undated
      - Digby, Henry and Susan, circa 1980, 1989-1996, (2 folders)
      - Digby, Rupert and Charlotte, 1975-1996, undated
      - Digby, Susannah, 1993, undated
      - Digby, Zara, 1980-1982, 1990-1996, undated
      - Dorset estate sale, 1979
      - Genealogy, 1973, undated
      - James, Chris, 1980, 1997, undated
      - James, Diana, 1974, 1986-1991
      - James, Jacquetta Digby, 1961, 1971-1996, undated
      - James, Michael, 1983-1986
      - James, Patsy, 1984-1994, undated
      - Miscellaneous relatives, 1945, 1996
      - Moore, Sheila Digby, 1962-1983, 1990-1997, undated
    - Harriman family (Box I:10)
      - Ames, Kathleen ("Kitty") Fisk
        - Campaign, 1982-1983, (2 folders)
        - General, 1973-1994, undated
      - Brice, Patricia Cullen, 1982-1988
      - Duchin, Peter, 1979-1985, undated
      - Fisk, Averell H., 1976-1996, undated
      - Fisk, Mary Averell Harriman, 1974-1996, undated
      - Fisk, Robert C. and Linda, 1972-1994, undated, (2 folders)
      - Gerry, Edward H., 1981, 1991
      - Gerry, Elbridge T. and Marjorie, 1979-1991, undated
      - Gerry, Henry Averell and Nancy, 1972, 1982, 1991
      - Harriman, E. Roland and Gladys, 1975-1978
      - Harriman, Marie Norton Whitney, card file for entertaining See Part I: Oversize
      - Harriman, W. Averell (husband)
        - Anniversary and birthday notes to and from Pamela Harriman, 1983-1985, undated
        - Artwork
          - Copley, John Singleton, Mary Montague and her brother Robert Copley, given to Digby family, 1972
          - Cox, Gardner, portrait of W. Averell Harriman, 1982-1988
          - Fraser, Laura Gardin, portrait of Mary W. Harriman, undated
          - Gogh, Vincent van, Roses, 1986-1993
          - List of works in residence, undated
          - Polo ponies, advice on captions and framing from the National Gallery of Art, 1985
        - Birthdays
          - Ninetieth, 1981 For additional material see Containers II:191-200, Ninetieth birthday celebration
          - Ninety-fourth, 1985
        - Death and funeral, 1986 (Box I:11)
          - Acknowledgment card design
          - Buffet supper at Kitty Carlisle Hart residence, New York, N.Y.
          - Burial, (2 folders)
          - Call lists, (3 folders)
          - Condolences
            - Acknowledged
              - A-G, (7 folders)
              - H-S, (10 folders) (Box I:12)
              - S-Z, (5 folders) (Box I:13)
            - Incoming
              - A-C See also Part I: Oversize, (4 folders)
              - C-H, (7 folders) (Box I:14)
              - H-O, (7 folders) (Box I:15)
              - P-W, (6 folders) (Box I:16)
              - Y-Z (Box I:17)
            - Lists, (2 folders)
            - Miscellaneous copies
            - "VIP and special", (5 folders)
          - Congressional tributes, (2 folders)
          - Death notices with photograph (Box I:18)
          - Donations to the Harriman Institute, 1986-1987
          - Flowers
          - In memoriam book
            - Correspondence
            - Galleys
            - Recipients, (2 folders)
            - Samples, 1965-1985, (2 folders)
            - Thank-you letters, 1986-1987
          - Last illness
          - Lists of names, 1985-1986
          - Miscellany (Box I:19)
          - News clippings
            - By place, (4 folders)
            - Instructions for handling
            - Scrapbook See Part I: Oversize
          - Notes, Janet A. Howard
          - Press
          - Prior planning, undated
          - Scrapbook of tributes and resolutions
          - Services (Box I:20)
            - Funeral, New York, N.Y.
              - Arrangements and planning
              - Guest book See also Part I: Oversize
              - Hymns and music, 1981-1986
              - Lists of names
              - Program
              - Seating
              - Ushers and pallbearers
            - General correspondence
            - Memorials
              - Sun Valley, Idaho
              - Washington, D.C.
                - Arrangements and planning
                - Attendees
                - Eulogies
                - Guest book See Part I: Oversize
                - Photographs, (2 folders)
                - Program, invitation, and press
                - Thank-you letters
                - Ushers
          - United Nations memorial book (Box I:21)
          - Washington, D.C., office memoranda
        - Declaration of gift to Pamela Harriman, 1982
        - Memoranda and lists regarding W. Averell Harriman's papers, 1981-1992, undated, (5 folders)
        - Miscellany, 1947-1955, 1963-1967, 1973, 1983, undated See also Part I: Oversize
        - Proposed biographies, 1988, undated
        - Scheduling notes, 1984-1985, undated
        - Wartime papers
          - Personal correspondence from
            - Harriman, Kathleen Lanier, to Pamela Harriman
              - 1943-1945
              - No year
                - Jan.-Dec., (4 folders)
                - Undated (Box I:22)
            - Harriman, Pamela, to W. Averell Harriman and Kathleen Lanier Harriman, 1943-1945, undated, (9 folders)
            - Harriman, W. Averell, message to Pamela Harriman with annotations by Harry L. Hopkins, 1942
        - Writings, statements, and speech notes
          - Draft on Ronald Reagan's foreign policy, 1983, (3 folders)
          - General, 1981-1983, undated
      - Mason, Phyllis Harriman, 1981, 1988-1991
      - Miscellaneous relatives, 1974-1977
      - Mortimer, Averell ("Avie") H. and Gigi Newhard, 1975-1993, undated, (2 folders) (Box I:23)
      - Mortimer, David H. and Shelley Wanger, 1975-1993, undated See also Part I: Oversize, (3 folders)
      - Mortimer, Jay L. and Prudence Bach, 1976-1993, undated
      - Mortimer, Kathleen Lanier Harriman, 1974-1994, undated, (3 folders)
      - Northrop, Edward H. ("Ned") and Christi Mueller, 1973-1993, undated
      - Photograph, 1955
      - Rumsey, Charles C. and Mary, 1976, 1984, 1991
      - Rumsey, Mary Averell H. ("Sis"), 1975-1989
      - Rumsey, Mary Harriman, 1932-1934
    - Hayward family
      - Christmas gift list, 1963
      - Davies, Weedie Sullavan, 1961-1963
      - Hayward, Bridget, 1977-1996, undated
      - Hayward, Brooke
        - Correspondence
          - From Brooke Hayward and Peter Duchin, 1985-1988, undated
          - Regarding house fire, 1961-1962
        - Haywire (Box I:24)
          - Clippings, 1977
          - Correspondence, 1976-1980
      - Hayward, Leland (husband)
        - Aronson, Steven M. L., biography, 1990-1994
        - Client list, undated
        - Ford 50th Anniversary Show, Emmy Awards, 1984-1989
        - Last illness, death, and funeral
          - Correspondence, 1971, (4 folders)
          - News clippings, 1971
          - Notes, undated
        - Miscellany, 1963-1967, 1974-1983, 1990-1991
        - New York Public Library, New York, N.Y., 1974
        - Royalties and copyright, 1985-1986
        - The Trial of the Catonsville Nine, 1971
      - Hayward, Leland, (grandson of Leland Hayward), 1974-circa 1993, undated
      - Hayward, William L., 1961-1965, 1976, 1989-1993
      - Hopper, Marin, circa 1970s, 1987
      - Notes, 1991
      - Tappin, Sarah Hayward, 1963, circa 1977
      - Thomas family, 1971-1993, undated
      - Young, Rita Hayward
        - 1973-1978
        - 1979-94, undated, (3 folders) (Box I:25)
    - Whitney family
      - Hurd, Christopher, 1981-1992
      - Hurd, Victoria, 1982-1989, undated
      - Lutz, Nancy Whitney, 1971-1972, 1986-1990
      - Morgan, Pamela and Alida, 1975-1976
      - Whitney, Alexandra Ewing, 1972-1977, 1989, undated
      - Whitney, C. Scollay, 1979-1986
      - Whitney, C. V. (Cornelius Vanderbilt), 1971, undated
      - Whitney, Gifford C., 1974-1975, 1992
      - Whitney, John Hay and Betsey Cushing Roosevelt, 1962, 1975-1982, undated
  - Personal Papers, 1920-1997 (Box I:25-I:34)
    Correspondence; lists; photographs; business records; passports and visas; birth, marriage, and naturalization certificates; a horoscope; a jewelry appraisal; and printed matter.
    Arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material.
    - Artwork (Box I:25)
      - Blackburn, David, "Trees and Stones," loan for exhibit, 1982
      - General, 1973-1992
      - Neman, Oscar, bust of Pamela Harriman, 1971-1974
      - Seurat, Georges, "Les Bucherons," loan for exhibit, 1989-1991
    - Correspondence
      - Achard, Marcel, undated
      - Acheson, Alice, with a menu signed by Syngman Rhee, 1956, 1972-1991, undated
      - Acland, Antony and Jennifer, 1986-1993, undated, (2 folders)
      - Aga Khan, Amyn, 1989-1991, undated
      - Agnelli, Giovanni and Marella
        - Correspondence regarding car crash, 1952
        - Letters to and from the Agnellis, 1962-1978, 1987-1990, undated
        - Printed matter, 1976, 1983-1989
      - Amery, Julian, 1971-1991
      - Astor, Brooke, 1967-1992, undated, (2 folders)
      - Baillie, Olive, and Pauline Cave, 1966-1980 (Box I:26)
      - Beaton, Cecil, 1971
      - Beaverbrook, Max Aitken, Baron, and Max Aitken, 1943, 1961-1964, 1972-1978, 1989
      - Berlin, Irving, 1983-1988
      - Blass, Bill, 1981-1989, undated
      - Brisson, Frederick and Rosalind Russell, 1971-1984, undated
      - Brown, J. Carter, 1974-1993
      - Carter, Jimmy and Rosalynn, 1976-1988, (2 folders)
      - Clinton, Bill, 1981-1993, undated See also Part I: Oversize, (3 folders)
      - Clinton, Hillary Rodham, 1980, 1992-1993
      - Colbert, Claudette, 1980-1989, undated
      - Collingwood, Charles, 1974-1985
      - Colville, Cynthia Crewe-Milnes, Lady, on behalf of Queen Mary, 1945
      - Colville, John Rupert, Sir, 1983-1987
      - Comden, Betty, 1977-1981, 1988-1991
      - Cooper, Diana, 1963, 1970-1984, undated
      - Cronyn, Hume, and Jessica Tandy, 1974-1975, 1982
      - De la Renta, Oscar, circa 1974-1983, undated
      - De Nervo, Monique, 1961-1963, 1974-1982
      - Devonshire, Deborah Vivien Freeman-Mitford Cavendish, Duchess of, 1979-1985, 1992
      - Druon, Maurice, 1961-1965, 1973
      - Eames, Charles and Ray, 1970-1977 (Box I:27)
      - Eden, Clarissa and Anthony, 1972-1993, (3 folders)
      - Fairbanks, Douglas, Jr., 1966, 1974-1988
      - Farrow, Mia, 1970
      - Fine, Sylvia, 1987
      - Fonda, Henry and Shirlee, 1968-1974, 1982, undated
      - Ford, Betty, 1976, 1983
      - Fraser, Donald W. and Gretchen, 1975-1993, undated, (5 folders)
      - Fraser, Hugh, Antonia, and Rebecca, 1961-1966, 1973-1989, undated
      - Gaulle, Charles de, 1943-1944, undated
      - General
        - 1943-1946, 1961-1963 See also Classified, (3 folders)
        - 1964-1978, (15 folders) (Box I:28)
        - 1979-1996, undated, (15 folders) (Box I:29)
      - Gilbert, Martin, 1940, 1986-1993 (Box I:30)
      - Gilbert, Sonja, 1974-1988, undated
      - Graham, Katherine, 1972-1992 [?], undated
      - Green, Adolph and Phyllis Newman, 1981-1989, undated
      - Guinness, Loel and Gloria, 1961-1981, 1989
      - Harrison, Rex and Mercier, 1982-1991, undated
      - Hart, Kitty Carlisle, 1961, 1971-1991, undated, (2 folders)
      - Hepburn, Katherine, 1967-circa 1975, 1982, 1991
      - Hopkins, Louise, 1944
      - Hornblow, Leonora and Arthur, 1961-1962, 1976-1987
      - Hungerford, Charles Frederick Algernon Portal, Viscount Portal of See Container I:31, Portal, Charles ("Peter")
      - Jenkins, Roy (1920-2003), 1973-1976, 1986, undated
      - Johnson, Lady Bird, 1973-1993, undated, (5 folders)
      - Johnson, Philip, 1971-1972 [?]
      - Kavanaugh, Kathleen Malley, 1971, 1979-1992
      - Kennedy, Edward M., and family, 1974-1992, (2 folders) (Box I:31)
      - Kennedy, Ethel and Robert F.
        - General, 1964-1991, undated
        - Valentines from Ethel Kennedy, 1978-1980, undated
      - Kennedy, Rose Fitzgerald, 1962, 1971-circa 1974, 1988
      - Lacy, Bill, 1989-1992
      - Lane, Kenneth Jay, 1973, 1982-1989
      - Lazar, Irving ("Swifty"), 1978-1990
      - Lieberson, Goddard and Vera Zorina, 1975-1978, 1986-1989
      - Lloyd, Geoffrey, 1973-1984, undated, (4 folders)
      - Logan, Joshua and Nedda Harrigan, 1966-1989, undated
      - Maclean, Fitzroy and Veronica, 1975-1992
      - Martin, Mary, 1973-circa 1977, 1984-1989
      - Niarchos, Stavros, 1963, 1973-1978, 1986-1989
      - Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, 1960-1962, circa 1970-1974, 1994-1995
      - Paley, William S., 1973-circa 1979, 1987-1988, undated
      - Parish-Hadley, 1981-1989, undated
      - Parsons, Drue and Geoffrey, 1972-1978, undated
      - Plesch, Etti, 1969-1977, 1988-1992
      - Portal, Charles ("Peter"), 1945, undated
      - Pritzker, Jay and Cindy, 1979, 1989, undated (Box I:32)
      - Ravenel, Zozo de, 1962, 1975-1978, 1987-1993